Guide to the Immanuel and Helen Olshan Texas Music Festival Records
University of Houston Libraries
Immanuel and Helen Olshan Texas Music Festival Records
1985-2013
1991-2013
09/2013-002
Texas Music Festival
4.00 linear feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
This collection contains materials produced by or related to the Immanuel and Helen Olshan Texas Music Festival held at the University of Houston. Collection materials date from 1985 to 2013, though the majority of materials are from 1991 to 2013.
Historical Note:
“The Immanuel and Helen Olshan Texas Music Festival ® was founded in 1990 to provide young professional musicians with a challenging musical environment in which to develop skills in orchestral, chamber music, and solo performance. The intensive four-week orchestral fellowship program on the University of Houston campus is guided by renowned guest conductors, members of Houston’s orchestras, faculty from the Moores and Shepherd schools of music, and other distinguished artists.
TMF also offers instructional institutes for musicians ranging in age from junior high to adult in a variety of specialty areas (voice, flute, piano & jazz). Each institute is highly selective and students are chosen by auditions and/or teacher recommendations. Institute instructors include world-class performers and teachers that come from Houston, other major cities in Texas, and from throughout the world. Institute participants are involved in large ensemble rehearsals, sectionals, lessons, coachings, and musicianship classes. Additionally, each of these institutes culminate in a final performance and many offer multiple performing opportunities.”
Source: University of Houston, Immanuel & Helen Olshan Texas Music Festival, http://www.uh.edu/class/music/tmf/
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
Moores School of Music; Texas Music Festival; Texas Music Festival. Orchestra
Genre/Form of Material:
Calendars; Clippings (information artifacts); Posters; Publications (document genre); Sound recordings
Topical Term:
Music Festivals -- Texas -- Houston
Acquisition Information:
Transferred to the University Archives by Alan Austin, General & Artistic Director, The Immanuel and Helen Olshan Texas Music Festival
Accruals:
Additional materials arrived December 4, 2013. Additional concert recordings are anticipated.
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research
Physical Characteristics or Technical Requirements:
Series 3 of this collection contains digital archival materials, which can be accessed in the Special Collections Reading Room by advance request. These materials may require up to one week to access. Contact curator Mary Manning (mmanning@uh.edu) for more information.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains materials produced by or related to the Immanuel and Helen Olshan Texas Music Festival held at the University of Houston. Collection materials date from 1985 to 2013, though the majority of materials are from 1991 to 2013. Materials are concentrated in the Houston area, though programs from concerts in Atlanta and Leipzig are also included.
Programs, concert schedules, festival calendars, unused application materials, invitations, correspondence, photographs, posters, publications, press clippings, a scrapbook, and numerous concert recordings are included. Also included is a Texas Music Festival Day Proclamation by Houston Major Bill White. Most of the later programs are included, but those from the 1990s are incomplete. The digital concert recordings date from 2000-2011, but holdings are incomplete.
Detailed List of Contents
- Programs
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains assorted Texas Music Festival Programs from 1992-2013. Included are Festival Programs and materials related to various TMF institutes and concerts. These include the Classical Minds Guitar Festival, Piano Institute, Jazz Institute, and Chamber Music Concerts. Programs have been arranged by date.
  - Festival Programs, 1992-2005 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Festival Programs, 2006-2009 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Festival Programs, 2009-2010 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Festival Programs, 2011-2012 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Festival Programs, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Classical Minds Guitar Festival, 2004-2010 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Other TMF institutes and concerts, 2005-2013 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Publicity and Press
  This series contains materials related to the promotion and coverage of the Texas Music Festival. Materials have been arranged by function, except for oversized materials which have been separated. Most promotional and press materials date from 1991-2013, though at least one poster dates from 1985. Many materials such as concert schedules, festival calendars, unused application materials, invitations, correspondence, photographs, and posters were produced by the Festival or its affiliates. The series also includes materials produced by other sources, including Festival coverage in magazines and press clippings. Also included is a scrapbook, which has been disbound and its contents placed into 6 folders. The scrapbook includes a variety of TMF materials such as programs, invitations, press clippings, and correspondence, which have been maintained together rather than sorted into the other series. Oversize materials in this series include oversize posters, photographs, and a Texas Music Festival Day Proclamation by Houston Major Bill White.
  - Concert Schedules and Festival Calendars, 1994-2013 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Publicity/recruitment materials for participants, 2007-2013 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Application materials, 1994-2011 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Invitations and correspondence, 1990-2011 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Photographs, 2001-2012 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Press clippings and printouts, 1991-2013 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - TMF in publications of other festivals and orchestras, 2005-2013 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - TMF in other publications, 2005-2011 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Scrapbook, undated (Box 1, Folder 16-21)
    disbound
  - OVS Festival posters, Mayoral Proclamation, Photographs, 1985-2012 (Drawer F.3, Ovs folder 9)
- Concert Recordings
  This series features concert recordings from the Texas Music Festival ranging from 2000-2011. Approximately 200 recordings are available in their entirety, and partial recordings are available for approximately 25 more. These recordings arrived in the archives on CDs, but have been transferred off of these fragile media. Recordings are available digitally and can be accessed in the Special Collections Reading Room by advance request. These materials may require up to one week to access. Contact curator Mary Manning (mmmanning@uh.edu) for more information.